10TH ANNIVERSARY COMMEMORATION
TOEI COMPANY LTD.
ANJU AND ZUSHIOU-MARU
Executive Producer: Hiroshi OKAWA
Producer: Isamu TAKAHASHI
Script: Sumie TANAKA
Directed by:
Taiji YABUSHITA, Yugo SERIKAWA
Animation Supervisor: Sanae YAMAMOTO
Music: Chuji KINOSHITA, Hajime KABURAGI
Lead Animators:
Akira DAIKUBARA, Yasuji MORI,
Yasuo OTSUKA, Hideo FURUSAWA,
Masao KUMAGAWA, Daikichiro KUSUBE
Animation: Shuji KONNO, Masatake KITA,
Reiko OKUYAMA, Makoto NAGASAWA,
Chikao TERA, Michihiko YOSHIDA,
Taku SUGIYAMA, Toyohei HORIKAWA
Art Director: Seiichi TORIIZUKA
Color Design: Reiji KOYAMA
Backgrounds: Mataji URATA
Saburo YOKOI, Hideo CHIBA
Research: Koji FUKIYA
Camera: Seigo OTSUKA,
Kazuo NAKAMURA, Takaharu AZUMA
Sound: Masatoshi KUGA,
Takeshi MORI, Hajime KIMURA
Editing: Shintaro MIYAMOTO, Ikuzo INABA
Ink: Mitsuo SHINDOU, Fumie MOTOHASHI,
Masako MIYAZAKI, Nobuko YOSHIDA
Paint: Fukiko HAYASHI,
Junko KAWASHIMA, Yoshiko NAKAJIMA
Checking: Saburo NIIRO
Song Lyrics: Chuji KINOSHITA
Singers: Tomoko MATSUSHIMA, Keiko NOZAWA
Cast:
Yoshiko SAKUMA, Jo MIZUKI, Kinya KITAOJI,
Isuzu YAMADA, Tomohito SUMIDA, Junya USAMI
So YAMAMURA, Tomoko MATSUSHIMA,
Mikijiro HIRA, Masao MISHIMA,
Yasushi NAGATA, Eijiro TONO
Nakajiro TOMITA, Masao ODA,
Ushio AKASHI, Harue TONE,
Shigeko ARAI, Tokue HANAZAWA
Junji MASUDA, Reiko MUTO,
Koji KIYOMURA, Koji SEKIYAMA,
Kenji USHIO, Toru OHIRA
Mother!
Where is Father?
He's out protecting the Emperor's land.
Let's go find him, Sister.
You may go.
Spring has come to Seven Mountains
Spring has come passing through the woods
With sweet voices,
The birds are singing
And the wind gently blows
Come, spring
Come, friends
The sun softly shines
It's Father!
Oh, Ranmaru! Good dog.
Father!
Anju and Zushio.
We came to get you.
Thank you. I was just about to head home.
Father,...
...the baby deer have already grown so much.
Yes, I see.
Oh, I hear a bear crying.
It hurts! It hurts!
You're exaggerating, Moku!
It's not that bad!
What happened, Chonko?
Oh, it's a big thorn.
It hurts.
Here...
You're alright now.
My Lord, the governor of Mutsu has come.
Onikura has come again?
I want you to give me
a definitive answer today.
Will you give me permission
to marry your daughter, Anju?
Mother...
What's going to happen?
Iwaki! What is your answer?
But Onikura, no matter how much you
want to marry her, she's still a child.
Of course. That's what makes her so sweet.
Besides, my daughter doesn't want to...
Alright. I understand.
However, Iwaki,...
...it would be more convenient for you
if you didn't decline my proposal.
I say this as your superior.
What do you mean?
Damn!
Why you little...
What's so funny?
It's hopeless, My Lord. Let's go home.
- Hey, start a fire over there!
- Yes, Sir.
Uh, we can't. Look.
"This land is the property of the Emperor."
"Hunting birds and animals is prohibited."
Never mind that!
My Lord!
Kill all the animals that run out!
Moku, it's terrible!
Moku, wake up right now! Moku!
Fire?
- Capture those animals!
- Yes.
Help!
Help us!
Moku!
Now you can't escape!
Stop!
Onikura, you are no longer in the mountains.
I captured that animal. Give it to me!
This bear belongs to the Emperor.
- No it doesn't!
- Yes, it lives on the reserve.
And it's my job to protect
everything on the Emperor's land.
What?
Are you defying your superior?
Father! This man set fire
to the Emperor's mountain!
Nonsense!
I found his bag of flint.
That's his crest!
And don't forget it!
"It's an outrage that Officer Masauji Iwaki
set fire to the Emperor's forest,"
"and killed all the animals.
Therefore, I submit this complaint."
"Imperial Order:"
"Officer Masauji Iwaki shall report
to Kyoto immediately for interrogation."
What's happening, Mother?
You need not worry.
Dear...
There's nothing to worry about.
I'll be back soon.
Why hasn't Father returned yet?
It's already been half a year.
Lord Onikura is here!
What now, Mother?
That's Onikura's voice!
By order of the Emperor,
I've come to claim this property.
Open the gate immediately!
No, I don't believe any of it.
What?
Come on, men!
Break it down!
Terrible news!
Your father has been found guilty,
and we must leave this house.
No way! This is Father's house.
He's not a bad man. It's a lie!
But for now we must escape.
That's true. Let's go find Father
and appeal to the Emperor.
Come, we must hurry!
My Lord, we can't find them anywhere.
They've escaped!
- Go find them!
- Yes!
Come on!
Time to say goodbye to our house.
Where did they run off to?
Seems like they tricked us.
Damn them!
Good work!
My Lord, let's just go home!
Nonsense!
This is nothing...
Come on, let's go.
Are you okay?
Moku, I'm cold.
Go to sleep, good children, go to sleep
Behind the mountains,
An owl is hooting
"Slave traders reported in this area."
"Be wary of offering
accomodations to strangers."
I want that bear.
Leave it to me.
Someone's coming.
Excuse me.
Ranmaru.
Who are you?
I live nearby.
I felt sorry for you, so I brought this.
Please, take it.
Thank you very much.
Where are you headed?
To the capital.
Oh, Kyoto?
There are many dangerous
areas on the way there.
It's difficult to go with children.
Actually, tomorrow there's
a boat that leaves for Yura.
Why not take that?
Thank you, good night.
It's nothing.
Oh, I almost forgot about
your loyal followers.
Here.
Tatsuko...
How does that sound to you?
Sounds good. Yamaoka Taifu
worked everything out.
Jinpachi, you're okay with the children?
Yeah, that's good.
Thanks for waiting.
Here, the children will take this boat.
What? We're taking separate boats?
Yes.
That way the boats travel faster.
Here, step on.
And the animals?
Huh? Oh...
When they arrive,
I'll take them in the next boat.
Come on, get those boats moving.
I think we've been drugged.
Moku, I can't move at all.
Which one is first?
What's going on?
We're drifting away from the other boat!
- Mother!
Let me steer!
Shut up!
You tricked us, didn't you?
Here, take this.
Just bring us to the other boat!
It's too late for that.
- Mother!
Anju!
Zushio!
Cry all you want, but it's useless.
What will you do with us?
Shut up! I'm selling you!
Mother!
Anju!
Zushio!
There's no use crying.
That boat's headed for the island of Sado.
Mother!
Anju!
Zushio!
Please, I beg you,
take us back to the other boat!
Enough!
Oh no!
Kikuno!
This is the residence
of the wealthiest man in Yura,...
...the High Steward Sansho.
Hiro, make sure this is finished in a month.
Yes, I will.
Get back to work!
Saburo, leave him.
High Steward, these are the ones I bought.
What are your names?
Answer.
What about you, boy?
Tell him.
Answer!
Gonroku, did you buy a pair of mutes?
No, I...
Speak, children!
Can you say anything or not?
Talk! I'm warning you!
You're responsible for this purchase.
I'll punish them.
Father...
They must be too hungry to speak.
What a horrible place.
Help me!
If you two try to escape from this place,
the same will happen to you.
Help!
This is for fetching water.
This is for gathering wood.
You will get up at the crack of dawn.
Answer "yes."
Yes.
I am the slavemaster, Gonroku.
If you disobey me...
Damn it!
- Stop it, Zushio.
- I'm so angry!
Zushio...
We must be patient, no matter what happens.
Alright?
Sure was easy to trick those idiots.
One of mine was trouble.
Too bad we lost her.
Gimme some more...
I'm pretty drunk.
Sea's getting rough.
Strange...
What's happening?
Forgive me!
Help!
Sorry!
Sister.
I can't work with so little to eat.
You can have mine too.
Here's some candy for you. Cheer up.
Take it.
Kikuno!
Ouch!
Thank you.
Here.
What?
- You're a strange boy.
- Why do you say that?
All of the animals like you.
I like the animals too.
I wonder where Moku and the others are...
By the way, what is your name?
I am Zushio-maru.
My father is Officer Masauji Iwaki.
What, an officer?
That's right.
He's kind and gentle to everyone.
I see. I envy you.
Anju.
- Let me help.
- No, I can do it myself.
Zushio has told me your whole story.
I've decided to forget about the past.
Anju...
Don't give up yet.
Sister, how do you think Mother is doing?
I think she's probably worried about us too.
On the shore of the lake, silently
Memories from long ago return to me
I can remember my mother's eyes
Those children are always fooling around.
It's true. They are stubborn too.
And the girl is getting
too friendly with Saburo.
What? With Saburo?
Father, will you punish Saburo?
No, just the girl.
Cut off her hair.
And give them harder work.
What are you doing?
Go away!
Zushio!
Wait! This is your warning!
Sister!
Zushio!
Just a dream...
You had one too?
Luckily it was only a dream.
Look, Zushio. What a beautiful sunset.
Yes.
Listen, on the other side of
that mountain lies Kokubunji Temple.
They say it's only
three days away from Kyoto.
- You should flee from here now.
- What?
Go to Kyoto and find Father.
Alone?
- Yes.
- No way!
- Let's go together!
- No.
- I would slow you down.
- No!
I won't go without you!
Zushio...
You should listen to your big sister.
But what if they punish you later?
I'll be fine. Saburo will help me.
You don't have to worry about me.
Now hurry, before they see you.
Sister!
Goodbye, Sister.
Zushio...
Be careful.
- Find him?
- No.
Idiot! You're too careless.
Bring me the sister.
Well? Where did your brother go?
I don't know.
Saburo, did you help the boy escape?
Jiro, send out men to find him.
Please, protect Zushio
and let him reach Kyoto safely.
Anju...
Saburo!
Kokubunji Temple is suspect.
We are Lord Sansho's men.
We're looking for a child.
Answer, or we'll break the door down.
Stop.
What?
Don't you know this temple?
With all due respect,
it's under the protection of the Emperor.
What?
Do you still want to enter by force?
Just try it.
Find out what happens
if you rebel against the Emperor.
Let's go.
Here, give this letter
to the Chief Advisor in Kyoto,...
...and ask him for help.
I will. Thanks for everything.
Take care.
Hey.
You've only given me trouble.
Now confess.
Or would you like this?
Or, instead of being punished,...
...how about marrying me?
- What do you say?
- No!
Why, you...
You insolent girl!
How's this?
Ah, Saburo!
Stop it, Brother!
What are you doing?
Anju, hurry!
Run away! Brother!
Go!
Anju!
Father, the building!
The saddest thing... The saddest thing...
About a wandering life...
Is sleeping on the floor
not knowing about tomorrow
Past the mountains,
Through the valleys,
From East to West
A cold wind chills...
To the bone
Shut up!
Anju!
Zushio!
No way!
That worked pretty well!
Yeah.
We're finally free.
Hurry, let's go!
YURA PARISH
I can smell Anju.
Anju.
Must be close.
Hey, hey! What are you doing?
Where did you come from?
Over there.
What are you looking for?
Well, like this...
Get it?
I don't get it!
Maybe here?
It's Anju!
You finally came.
I really hope we find Zushio.
Kyoto is far away...
Zushio!
Princess, the cherry trees have blossomed.
Wow, how pretty!
Cherry blossoms, cherry blossoms,
Invited by spring in Kyoto
Called forth by Kiyomizu Temple
From the heart of a young maiden...
Comes a prayer
Cherry blossoms, cherry blossoms,
Kiyomizu Temple...
Help!
Why don't you come with me?
What are you doing?
Stop it!
- Who are you?
- Leave her alone!
You little brat!
Go away!
Brat!
It's Zushio!
You're right, it's him!
Out of the way!
- Zushio!
I'm so glad to see you!
Get him!
Thank you.
You are very strong.
Thank you very much for saving us.
I am Princess Aya,
Morozane Fujiwara's daughter.
What? Isn't he the Emperor's Chief Advisor?
I understand your situation.
So you came all the way here
in search of your father?
Yes.
I see. Well...
...your father is no longer here.
What? Why not?
He was found guilty, and ha exiled to Kyushu.
Please, Father,
send out a messenger right away.
I will.
Anju!
Zushio,
Father told me...
Hmm? About what?
He's going to help you study...
...about literature and martial arts.
Do your best.
Yes.
Sir Masauji has passed away.
What?
But how did he...?
What did my father die from?
Unfortunately it was
due to a prolonged illness or so have I heard.
I see.
I'm very sorry.
Zushio...
I understand your sadness,...
...but you're still a  young boy, and you
can't let misfortune overwhelm you.
Think of me as your father now.
Stay here and continue your studies.
Then you'll be able to
save your mother and sister.
All right?
Yes.
Ouch!
Can you take a little break?
Yes.
Zushio...
Have you heard the news from the Palace?
No. What happened?
Lately, they've been speaking
about a horrible monster...
...that comes to the Emperor's room at night.
- What? A monster?
- Yes.
If it continues,
the Emperor's life may be in danger.
My father told me.
Are you Zushio?
Yes.
The feat you have
accomplished is truly outstanding.
- Morozane.
- Yes.
Zushio, congratulations.
You are now the Governor of Mutsu Province.
And Taira-no-Masamichi is your new name.
Thank you.
May you become as
great a man as your father.
Yes.
Onikura, who had falsely accused your father,...
...shall be stripped of his post and punished.
Thank you for everything.
I will visit your province
when I have the chance.
Yes, you'll be welcome there.
You take care, Princess Aya.
Yes, you too.
Good-bye.
Father!
Zushio has become Governor
of Mutsu and he's headed here!
What? Zushio?
Yes, that boy who ran away.
Jiro.
Got it?
Don't mess up.
Go!
Why, you!
Retreat!
- Gonroku.
- Yes?
Thank you for coming out to welcome me.
Of course.
Good. I have not come here to punish you.
I want to see my sister.
She is...
Where is my sister?
Well... you see...
What have you done with her?
- You are...
- Yes, I am Saburo.
But your clothes...
Yes, the truth is...
Zushio.
I deeply regret what has happened.
Please forgive my father and brother.
- Lord Sansho.
- Yes?
Release all your slaves and
let them return to their homes today.
- But that's...
- You refuse? The Emperor demands it.
Yes.
Saburo.
Please take good care of my sister.
I will.
Do not worry.
I hope you find your mother.
How I miss you, Anju
How I miss you, Zushio
If you understand my words,
Go away birds, and be good
How I miss you, Anju
How I miss you, Zushio
Mother!
Mother! It's me, Zushio!
Zushio!
Look, it's Anju.
Yes.
Even with these eyes,
I can see a white bird.
You know, Zushio,...
...maybe she is happy living that way.
THE END